<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study>
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on April 09, 2025</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00076674</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>040101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>04-N-0101</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00076674</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Levetiracetam Treatment of L-dopa Induced Dyskinesias</brief_title>
  <official_title>Levetiracetam Treatment of L-dopa Induced Dyskinesias</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>This study will evaluate the effects of levetiracetam (Keppra (Trademark) on Parkinson's&#xd;
disease symptoms and on dyskinesias (involuntary movements) that develop as a result of&#xd;
long-term treatment with levodopa. Levetiracetam blocks certain protein receptors on&#xd;
brain cells and thus can change the spread of brain signals believed to be affected in&#xd;
patients with Parkinson's disease.&#xd;
&#xd;
Patients between 30 and 80 years of age with relatively advanced Parkinson's disease and&#xd;
dyskinesias due to levodopa therapy may be eligible for this 6-week study.&#xd;
&#xd;
Screening and baseline evaluation - Participants are evaluated with a medical history,&#xd;
physical examination and neurologic evaluation, blood tests, urinalysis,&#xd;
electrocardiogram (EKG), 24-hour holter monitor (heart monitoring), and cardiology&#xd;
consultation. A chest x-ray and MRI or CT scan of the brain are done if needed. If&#xd;
possible, patients stop taking all antiparkinsonian medications except levodopa (Sinemet)&#xd;
for one month (2 months if taking Selegiline) before the study begins and throughout its&#xd;
duration. (If necessary, patients may use short-acting agents, such as Mirapex, Requip or&#xd;
Amantadine.)&#xd;
&#xd;
Dose-finding phase - Patients are admitted to the NIH Clinical Center for 2 to 3 days for&#xd;
a levodopa "dose-finding" procedure. For this test, patients stop taking Sinemet and&#xd;
instead have levodopa infused through a vein. During the infusions, the drug dose is&#xd;
increased slowly until parkinsonian symptoms improve or unacceptable side effects occur&#xd;
or the maximum study dose is reached. Symptoms are monitored frequently. (Patients who&#xd;
have had dosing infusions in the last 3 months do not have to undergo this phase of the&#xd;
study.)&#xd;
&#xd;
Active study phase - Patients are randomly assigned to take levetiracetam or placebo&#xd;
("sugar pill") twice a day for 6 weeks. At the end of weeks 1, 2 4, and 5, patients come&#xd;
to the clinic for blood tests, an EKG, and a review of adverse side effects. At the end&#xd;
of weeks 3 and 6, patients are hospitalized to study the response to treatment. They&#xd;
again stop taking Sinemet and selegiline and their ability to perform motor tasks is&#xd;
evaluated. They are then placed on an L-dopa infusion for 10 hours. Placebo may be&#xd;
infused at various times instead of L-dopa. Motor symptoms are evaluated several times&#xd;
during the infusion. Blood is drawn once during the infusion for research studies.&#xd;
&#xd;
Lumbar puncture - Patients undergo a lumbar puncture (spinal tap) at the end of weeks 1&#xd;
and 4 to measure certain brain chemicals and drug levels. For this test, a local&#xd;
anesthetic is given and a needle is inserted in the space between the vertebrae in the&#xd;
lower back. About 2 tablespoons of fluid is collected through the needle.&#xd;
&#xd;
Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) - Patients with changing disease activity may undergo&#xd;
MRIs at baseline, at the end of week 1 and at the end of the study to show changes in the&#xd;
brain. The patient lies in a narrow cylinder (the scanner) that uses radio waves and a&#xd;
magnetic field to produce images of the brain, which show structural and chemical&#xd;
changes.&#xd;
&#xd;
Follow-up - 2 weeks after the study ends, patients are contacted by phone for a review of&#xd;
side effects or they return to the clinic for an evaluation.</textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>Introduction: Parkinson's disease is a progressive degenerative disease of unknown&#xd;
etiology. Its treatment has been symptomatic and the most successful approach has been to&#xd;
replace the missing dopamine through administration of its precursor levodopa. As the&#xd;
disease progresses the usefulness of this approach gradually diminishes and motor&#xd;
complications become a source of significant disability. Although a number of&#xd;
pharmacological strategies have attempted to improve this situation, none has yet proven&#xd;
fully satisfactory. The mechanism by which levetiracetam exerts this beneficial effect is&#xd;
unknown. Recently, in a PD monkey model levetiracetam was found to moderate dyskinesias&#xd;
and other motor complications, possibly due to its effects on striatal GABAergic&#xd;
transmission.&#xd;
&#xd;
Objective: To evaluate the acute ability of levetiracetam to safely ameliorate&#xd;
dopaminomimetic-treatment-associated dyskinesias and related motor complications in&#xd;
parkinsonian patients without compromising the antiparkinsonian response.&#xd;
&#xd;
Study Population: 22 moderately advanced parkinsonian patients will be enrolled into a&#xd;
randomized, placebo controlled, double-blind proof-of-principle study. Levetiracetam&#xd;
efficacy will be assessed through the use of validated motor function scales. Safety will&#xd;
be monitored by means of frequent clinical evaluations and laboratory tests.&#xd;
&#xd;
Anticipated Risks and Benefits: The potential risks associated with this study amount to&#xd;
only a minor increase over minimal risk and are primarily associated with adverse&#xd;
reactions to the medications involved. Levetiracetam is a marketed drug with a wide&#xd;
margin of safety. Patients receiving drug could benefit from improvement of their&#xd;
symptoms, those on placebo will also have their medications adjusted, leading to an&#xd;
improved quality of life.&#xd;
&#xd;
Outcome Estimate and Potential Meaning for the Field: This study should further the&#xd;
understanding of mechanisms contributing to motor disability in patients with PD that may&#xd;
lead to the development of improved therapeutic interventions for this disorder and for&#xd;
associated motor response complications.</textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>40</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyskinesias</condition>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intravenous Levodopa</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xd;
&#xd;
Patients who meet all of the following inclusion criteria will be able to participate in&#xd;
the study:&#xd;
&#xd;
  1. Patient is between the ages of 30 and 80, inclusive;&#xd;
&#xd;
  2. Patient has been diagnosed with idiopathic Parkinson's disease based on the presence&#xd;
     of a characteristic clinical history and neurological findings;&#xd;
&#xd;
  3. Patient has relatively advanced disease with levodopa-associated motor response&#xd;
     complications, including peak-dose dyskinesias and wearing-off fluctuations ;&#xd;
&#xd;
  4. Patient is willing to adhere to protocol requirements as evidenced by written,&#xd;
     informed consent.&#xd;
&#xd;
EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xd;
&#xd;
Patients meeting any of the following exclusion criteria will not be enrolled or&#xd;
immediately withdrawn from the study, as appropriate:&#xd;
&#xd;
  1. Patient has a history of any medical condition that can reasonably be expected to&#xd;
     subject them to unwaranted risk;&#xd;
&#xd;
  2. Patient has clinically significant laboratory abnormalities including impaired renal&#xd;
     function (CL(cr) equals 30-50 ml/min.);&#xd;
&#xd;
  3. Patient is uable to br treated with levodopa/carbidopa alone or with a single,&#xd;
     relatively short-acting dopamine agonist, such as pramipexole or ropinirole;&#xd;
&#xd;
  4. Patient is taking a prohibited concomitant medication;&#xd;
&#xd;
  5. Patient has not been using or was not continuing to use an adequate contraceptive&#xd;
     method for the last 30 days, or is not at least one year post-menopausal (if&#xd;
     female);&#xd;
&#xd;
  6. Patient is pregnant or breastfeeding;&#xd;
&#xd;
  7. Patient is implanted with bilateral deep brain stimulators;&#xd;
&#xd;
  8. Patient has prior pallidotomy or other ablative surgeries for treatment of PD;&#xd;
&#xd;
  9. Patient has cognitive impairment (MMSE less than 25);&#xd;
&#xd;
 10. Patient has participated in a clinical study with an investigational drug within the&#xd;
     last 30 days;&#xd;
&#xd;
 11. Patient has a condition (such as active drug or alcohol abuse) that, in the opinion&#xd;
     of the investigators, would interfere with compliance or safety;&#xd;
&#xd;
 12. Patient is unwilling to sign an informed consent or to comply with protocol&#xd;
     requirements;&#xd;
&#xd;
 13. Patient has a history of psychiatric illness.</textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernheimer H, Birkmayer W, Hornykiewicz O, Jellinger K, Seitelberger F. Brain dopamine and the syndromes of Parkinson and Huntington. Clinical, morphological and neurochemical correlations. J Neurol Sci. 1973 Dec;20(4):415-55. doi: 10.1016/0022-510x(73)90175-5. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>4272516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kish SJ, Shannak K, Hornykiewicz O. Uneven pattern of dopamine loss in the striatum of patients with idiopathic Parkinson's disease. Pathophysiologic and clinical implications. N Engl J Med. 1988 Apr 7;318(14):876-80. doi: 10.1056/NEJM198804073181402.</citation>
    <PMID>3352672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mizuno Y, Mori H, Kondo T. Parkinson's disease: from etiology to treatment. Intern Med. 1995 Nov;34(11):1045-54. doi: 10.2169/internalmedicine.34.1045.</citation>
    <PMID>8774962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2005</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 29, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Keppra</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor Fluctuations</keyword>
  <keyword>Intravenous Levodopa</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiparkinsonian Response</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>PD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyskinesias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <mesh_term>Levodopa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
</clinical_study>
