<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study>
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on April 09, 2025</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT00071045</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>040012</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>04-H-0012</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00071045</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Collection of Tissue Specimens From Patients With Solid Tumors or Blood Disorders and Their HLA-Compatible Family Members</brief_title>
  <official_title>Collection of Blood, Bone Marrow, Urine, and/or Tissue Samples From Patients With Solid Tumors, Hematological Malignancies or Non-Malignant Hematologic Disorders or HLA Compatible Family Members</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>This study will collect biological samples for use in research experiments aimed at&#xd;
better understanding the clinical features of certain diseases. The specimens may be used&#xd;
to evaluate the effectiveness of known therapies, refine treatment approaches, identify&#xd;
potential new therapies, and explore opportunities for disease prevention.&#xd;
&#xd;
The following individuals 2 years of age or older may be eligible for this study:&#xd;
&#xd;
  -  Patients with a cancerous solid tumor or a cancerous or non-cancerous blood disorder&#xd;
     who are being screened for or who are enrolled in a treatment study at the NIH&#xd;
     Clinical Center&#xd;
&#xd;
  -  HLA-compatible donor family members (18 years of age or older) of the above patients&#xd;
     who are being evaluated for or are enrolled in an NIH study as a stem cell&#xd;
     transplant donor&#xd;
&#xd;
  -  Patients with a cancerous solid tumor or a cancerous or non-cancerous blood disorder&#xd;
     or a bone marrow failure condition who cannot participate in an NIH treatment&#xd;
     protocol or travel to the NIH Clinical Center and who are referred for participation&#xd;
     through their home health care provider.&#xd;
&#xd;
Research samples will be collected from participants when blood is drawn or bone marrow,&#xd;
urine, or stool is collected, or tumor or other tissue is biopsied as part of their&#xd;
general medical care. Investigators may periodically request an additional sample of&#xd;
blood, stool, or urine. Participants who are 18 years of age or older may donate a large&#xd;
number of white blood cells through a procedure called leukapheresis. This procedure is&#xd;
not part of general medical care and would be done for research purposes only. For&#xd;
apheresis, a catheter (plastic tube) is placed in a vein in the subject's arm. Blood&#xd;
flows from the vein into a cell separator machine, where the white cells are separated&#xd;
from the red cells, platelets, and plasma by a spinning process. The white cells are&#xd;
removed and collected, and the rest of the blood is returned to the subject through a&#xd;
second tube placed in the other arm.</textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>The purpose of this protocol is to collect blood, bone marrow, urine, stool, oral&#xd;
samples, nasopharyngeal samples and/or both malignant and non-malignant tissue from&#xd;
patients who are either being evaluated for enrollment, are consented to NIH Clinical&#xd;
Center treatment protocols, or are receiving therapy for their disease through home&#xd;
health care providers. Since a substantial proportion of the clinical and translational&#xd;
research in the NHLBI involves patients undergoing allogeneic stem cell transplantation,&#xd;
this protocol will also be open to people identified as suitable HLA compatible donors&#xd;
for patients undergoing evaluation for or already enrolled in an allogeneic stem cell&#xd;
transplant protocol or receiving a stem cell transplant through their home health care&#xd;
providers. These HLA compatible donors will serve as a source of peripheral blood&#xd;
mononuclear cells (peripheral blood draws or leukapheresis) for use in evaluating&#xd;
allogeneic graft versus host and graft-versus-tumor effects.&#xd;
&#xd;
The primary objective is to provide a mechanism for collection, tracking, storing,&#xd;
dispensing, analyzing, and disposing of these laboratory research samples from patients&#xd;
and HLA matched donors.&#xd;
&#xd;
There is no primary endpoint.</textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 8, 2003</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biospecimen storage</measure>
    <time_frame>onging</time_frame>
    <description>Biospecimen storage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6000</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Hematologic Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients undergoing allogeneic stem cell transplantation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>HLA compatible donors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>The subject carries the diagnosis of malignant solid tumor or a malignant or&#xd;
non-malignant hematologic disorder; carries the diagnosis of malignant solid tumor or a&#xd;
malignant or non-malignant hematologic disorder; is a HLA-compatible family member of a&#xd;
patient (bearing a diagnosis of malignant solid tumor or a malignant or non-malignant&#xd;
hematologic disorder) being evaluated for or already enrolled on a clinical protocol at&#xd;
the NIH Clinical Center and is identified as a potentially suitable donor of allogeneic&#xd;
hematopoietic stem cells for transplantation; carries the diagnosis of malignant solid&#xd;
tumor or a malignant or non-malignant hematologic disorder or a bone marrow failure&#xd;
condition and is not available to participate in an NIH Clinical Center treatment&#xd;
protocol, or travel to the NIH Clinical Center, but is referred for participation through&#xd;
their home health care provider.</textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>  -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xd;
&#xd;
The subject carries the diagnosis of malignant solid tumor or a malignant or&#xd;
non-malignant hematologic disorder, and is being screened at the NIH for eligibility for&#xd;
an NIH protocol.&#xd;
&#xd;
OR&#xd;
&#xd;
The subject carries the diagnosis of malignant solid tumor or a malignant or&#xd;
non-malignant hematologic disorder, and is already enrolled on a protocol at the NIH&#xd;
Clinical Center.&#xd;
&#xd;
OR&#xd;
&#xd;
The subject is a related HLA-compatible family member of a patient (bearing a diagnosis&#xd;
of malignant solid tumor or a malignant or non-malignant hematologic) being evaluated for&#xd;
or already enrolled on a protocol at the NIH Clinical Center and is identified as a&#xd;
potentially suitable donor of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cells for transplantation.&#xd;
&#xd;
OR&#xd;
&#xd;
The subject carries the diagnosis of malignant solid tumor or a malignant or non&#xd;
malignant hematologic disorder or a bone marrow failure condition and is not available to&#xd;
participate in an NIH Clinical Center treatment protocol, or travel to the NIH clinical&#xd;
center, but is referred for participation through their home health care provider.&#xd;
&#xd;
The subject or the subject's Legally Authorized Representative (LAR) is able to&#xd;
understand the investigational nature of the study and provide informed consent after&#xd;
initial counseling by an AI. Separate consent forms for interventional or surgical&#xd;
procedures will be obtained after explanation of the specific procedure.&#xd;
&#xd;
Age 2 years and older (no upper limit)&#xd;
&#xd;
EXCLUSION CRITERIA:&#xd;
&#xd;
Subjects or LAR unable to comprehend the investigational nature of the protocol.&#xd;
&#xd;
Age less than 2 years</textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard W Childs, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bretagne Cowling, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 827-3479</phone>
    <email>bretagne.cowling@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Richard W Childs, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-7128</phone>
    <email>childsr@nhlbi.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY dial 711</phone_ext>
      <email>ccopr@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2004-H-0012.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 18, 2025</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 9, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 10, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2025</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2025</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2025</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tissue Procurement</keyword>
  <keyword>Sample Collection</keyword>
  <keyword>Laboratory Research Specimens</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
</clinical_study>
